Guide to the Oscar Berland Papers TAM.689
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Oscar Berland Papers
1936-2000
1950-1958
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Berland, Oscar Morris, 1927-
Johnson, Claudia Durst, 1938-
TAM.689
0.25 Linear Feet in 1 half manuscript box
Oscar Morris Berland (1927- ) is a political activist and writer who was raised in the United Workers Cooperative Colony, better known as "The Coops," during the Great Depression. The Oscar Berland Papers consist of biographical materials that date between the late 1930s and the year 2000, although the majority of the collection is from the 1950s. Included in the collection are photographic reproductions of Berland (age 12 through his mid-20s), a copy of Berland's FBI file (1951-1964), and a copy of a booklet of Berland's poetry (2000). The collection also includes some published information about the United Workers Co-op.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Oscar Berland with the assistance of Claudia Durst Johnson in 2016. The accession number associated with this gift is 2016.045.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical / Historical
Oscar Morris Berland (1927- ) is a political activist and writer who was raised in the United Workers Cooperative Colony during the Great Depression. The United Workers Co-Op, better known as "The Coops," was a commune located in the Allerton neighborhood of the East Bronx. It was built in 1927 primarily by first-generation Americans from a number of trades and became, at its time of construction, the largest co-op in the United States. The residents, which included immigrant and African American families, enjoyed a variety of amenities, including landscaped gardens, a library, gym, and classroom. These ideals inspired Berland's interest in American labor movements – more specifically Communism's agenda towards advancing the working-class – and his interest in equality during the Civil Rights Movement.
In 1948, after attending the City College of New York (CCNY), Berland went underground as a Communist labor organizer in Birmingham, Alabama. He was arrested numerous times, once for distributing pamphlets that identified a policeman as the bomber of a black family's home. Berland eventually moved to a Communist underground in the textile mills of North Carolina, where he resided until 1967. His work there as one of the three key "colonizers" prompted his being outed by the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC). Berland remained under the FBI's radar even after moving to California.
In California, Berland aspired to write a history of the Kaweah Colony, an experimental socialist colony that was located in what is now Sequoia National Park. Although his Kaweah Colony project was never realized, Berland is the author of several scholarly publications, most notably Aborted Revolution: A Study in the Formative Years of the American Labor Movement, 1877-1886, with Special Reference to the International Workmen's Association of San Francisco (1966) and "The Emergence of the Communist Perspective on the 'Negro Question' in America: 1919-1931" (1999-2000).
Content Description
The Oscar Berland Papers consist of biographical materials assembled by Oscar Berland during the course of his lifetime as a political activist and writer. Materials date between the late 1930s and the year 2000, although the majority of the collection is from the 1950s. Included in the collection are photographic reproductions of Berland (age 12 through his mid-20s), a copy of Berland's FBI file (1951-1964), and a copy of a booklet of Berland's poetry (2000). The collection also includes some published information about the United Workers Cooperative Colony (better known as "The Coops"), a housing cooperative in the Allerton neighborhood of the East Bronx where Berland was raised during the Great Depression.
Housing, Cooperative -- United States -- 20th century.; Communism -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; United Workers' Association (New York, N.Y.); Johnson, Claudia Durst, 1938-
- Photographs, circa 1936-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- The Coops: The United Workers Cooperative Colony, 50th Anniversary, 1927-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Oscar Berland's FBI Report, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Museum of the City of New York: In The Bronx, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Communism in Alabama, 1950-1951, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Poetry, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 18)